Hi everyone, welcome. Today we're
going to be covering APIs and large
scale data collection.
This lecture is not about memorizing
syntax, it's about developing a
workflow mindset.
The goal is to help you think about
APIs as a system, data collection as
a pipeline, failure as normal, scale
as transformative,
reproducibility as non-ecosable.
When you move from collecting 100
records to collecting 1 million,
everything changes. Your mindset has
to change with it.
So, what do APIs matter for social
science data? Let's begin with this.
So, in contemporary social science
research, many of the largest data
sets are not
downloaded as static CSV files.
They're accessed through Application
Programming Interfaces, or APIs.
These have structured endpoints,
machine readable responses.
And Application Programming
Interface, or API, is a formal
mechanism that allows one computer
system to request and
receive data from another.
The API is often the intended
interface for data access. This
matters for three reasons.
First, APIs are structured. The data
are organized in
unpredictable format.
Second, APIs are monitored. The
provider can track usage.
Third, APIs are controlled. Access
and limits are governed.
So, when an API exists, you should
treat it as a canonical interface.
It reflects how the data provider
wants the data to be accessed.
So, an API is not just a technical
tool. It's a contract.
It specifies what data can be
requested, or how requests must be
structured, what constraints apply
to usage, what
authentication is required,
and what response
format will be returned.
APIs encode institutional and
technical choices. They define what
is visible and what is invisible,
what is searchable, what is
filterable, and
what's afraid limited.
These are design
decisions. They're not neutral.
So, if the field has not been
exposed, it may as
well not exist for you.
If the filter is allowed, your
research question becomes feasible.
So, when using an API, you are
operating within someone else's
governing structure.
So, let's clarify the difference
between APIs and scraping.
APIs expose structure explicitly.
They return structured responses.
They enforce rules formally. They
log usage and then
provide documentation.
On the other hand, web scraping
extracts information from HTML
pages, recovers structure from
presentation ordered content,
often relies on brittle selectors,
and can break when layout changes.
The key difference is this. Scraping
recovers structure, APIs declare.
If an API exists and provides what
you need, it's almost always more
stable and more
reproducible than scraping.
Scraping is often a last resort when
APIs do not expose data.
So, most social science APIs return
data in JSON format. JSON stands for
JavaScript Object Notation.
So, you're going to commonly
encounter things like objects that
are key-value pairs, arrays and
lists, nested structure.
The critical insight here is that
understanding structure
matters more than syntax.
The technical act of sending a GET
request is trivial.
The hard part is inspecting the
response, understanding its nesting,
mapping into a relational structure,
and then preserving the metadata.
The conceptual skill
is structural reasoning.
So, JSON represents hierarchical
data. It contains objects, arrays,
nested hierarchies.
The important conceptual line is
that APIs are going to
return trees, not tables.
So, in other words, our response is
often we have the metadata, results,
ID1, ID2, and these are going to
correspond to our different data.
This is not flat. It's going to be
in a hierarchical structure or tree.
So, your job is often to extract the
branch of that tree, flatten the
nested fields, and then
preserve the relationships.
You're going to be converting
tree-shaped data
into table-shaped data.
This transformation is interpretive.
You decide which branches matter.
Most APIs require authentication.
Authentication methods include API
keys, bearer tokens, or OAuth flows.
Authentication is going to govern
things like access rights, rate
limits, attribution, audit trials.
But there are two best practices.
The first is you want to treat your
credentials as secret.
So, never hard-code tokens and
descript so it will
be shared or committed.
And then you go in and use things
like environmental variables.
So, you want to configure files that
exclude from version
control and secure storage.
And then second, authentication
defines your scope.
Some endpoints are only accessible
with elevated privileges.
So, your authentication
level shapes your dataset.
So, here's a minimal Python example.
You want to import your request.
You want to define a URL. You want
to define, pass
your parameters rather.
You want to add in
headers in this case.
You want to pull response and then
parse the data here.
So, this is just
parsing your JSON on it.
So, a JSON response can represent an
error just as easily as the data.
You never assume that this outcome
here means that it was successful.
You always have to check it.
And I've had projects too where I
thought I was scraping data.
The whole time I was hitting a rate
limit that I didn't realize and I
was returning a lot
of empty JSON files
and I had to go
back and redo it again.
So, this is a pretty common issue
and something you spend a lot of
time focusing on when you're doing
large-scale polling data.
And here's a similar version of R.
We have our website here. We're
getting a response with the URL
querying 100,
adding our headers here,
and then we are taking
out the response here.
So, the APIs rarely
return all records at once.
Why is this? Well first, large
responses strain servers.
They encourage inefficient use and
they reduce system stability.
So common pagination patterns
include things like page numbers,
offsets, cursor based pagination,
and then time window slicing.
So cursor based pagination is
especially common
in modern page APIs.
So instead of page one, page two,
page three, you get
a next cursor token.
So pagination logic becomes part of
your data generating process.
Your data set exists because you
loop over tourist
pages in a specific order.
So this is an example how we do
this. We have our all items.
This is turning to page one. So
while true, we are
looping through this page here.
We're pulling it with our response.
If not, we break it and we append.
In the same kind of syntax here
where we have all of our items,
paging one, and repeating this here,
we're pulling over for a
page here, one plus one.
So we're just iterating over the
same kind of process.
So rate limits
protect infrastructure.
Common constraints include things
like requests per second, requests
per minute, requests per day,
and then burst limits. So violating
your limits can result in things
like an HTTP 429 error.
That's what the problem was with the
project where I
thought I was pulling data,
but I was actually just getting a
bunch of empty JSON files.
You can have temporary bands if you
continue to file these things.
And then also permanent reallocation
if you continue to
circumvent the rules on it.
But basically what you need to take
away from here is that rate limits
shape visibility.
They constrain what can be collected
within a time window, and they're
not really technical.
They shape research design.
So as a best practice, you want to
set a sleeper between your requests.
Here in this table here, we're
sleeping for one second.
You want to read rate limit headers,
back off when there's an error, and
then implement exponential back off.
So exponential back
off, what does that mean?
If the first retry
fails, wait one second.
If the second retry fails, wait two
seconds, four seconds, eight
seconds, and so forth.
And this is a way to
stabilize your pipeline on it.
And I built all this in my code when
I'm doing large API extraction.
So what are retries and failures?
So at scale, failure is really
normal when you're using an API.
You want to expect things like
network interruptions, server
time-mails, malformed responses,
transient errors.
Your pipeline must assume there's
going to be failure built into it.
And so you need to code in things
like resilience to
design so it's not accidental.
And so when you get a failure, it
repeats and checks again.
And here's an example of retry logic
where we're setting it three times a
retry, try for a response here.
If it fails, we're sleeping for two
seconds, you want to be building an
exponential sleep here.
And then if it happens
three times, it moves on.
So logging is not optional.
In this case, it matters because we
want to track things
like failures, right?
But we also want to look at things
like what was requested and when it
was requested with what parameters.
What status code was returned and
how many records were received.
Logs are going to allow you to do
things like partial reruns, failure
points, data boundaries.
But logging is part
of reproducibility.
If you cannot reconstruct your
collection process, the
dataset is not auditable.
So another thing we're going to talk
about is storing bra API responses.
One thing is to run bra JSON files.
You don't want to overwrite these
necessarily, right?
And you want to have separate raw
data for your process data on it.
So I have like a separate, the one
bad part of this is JSON files can
be quite large for
storage purposes, right?
So for that project that I was
discussing earlier, I actually had
to buy an external hard drive for
all this JSON data on it.
Even though the CSV files are much
smaller, I want to be able to keep
the raw data so I bought
an external drive for it.
But in general, you want to keep
your APIs for replication or rather
your raw JSON files
for replication purposes.
So it's also very important in this
case to document.
You want to have your endpoint URL,
parameters that were used, the
authentication type,
the collection date, the API version
that you're working with, and then
any known constraints.
And the reason being
this is that APIs evolve,
fields might disappear,
defaults might change,
endpoints might deprecate.
So without this kind of information,
your dataset becomes
uninterpretable over time.
So what do we emphasize in practice?
You want to treat APIs as an
institutional artifact.
You want to inspect
structure before modeling,
expect failure at scale, preserve
raw data and logs.
And these principles
convert fragile scripts
into robust pipelines.
So let's just close with a
couple of thoughts, right?
So APIs are going to
embed your assumptions.
They reflect
governance, they shape visibility,
they're going to
constrain your scale.
And when you use an API, you're not
just collecting data,
you're participating in a structured
informational ecosystem.
So you want to
understand that ecosystem
as part of a
responsible data science.
And that's going to be it for today.